<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tony De La Nuez</title>
    <link>https://tdoot.com/writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Tony De La Nuez</description>
    <image>
      <title>Tony De La Nuez</title>
      <url>https://tdoot.com/images/pictures/portrait.jpg</url>
      <link>https://tdoot.com/images/pictures/portrait.jpg</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 22:18:21 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://tdoot.com/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>(WIP) - WTF is a WAV</title>
      <link>https://tdoot.com/writing/wtf-is-a-wav/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 22:18:21 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tdoot.com/writing/wtf-is-a-wav/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today on a walk I started thinking about audio files, so I tried to reason through them from first principles.
The main question was &amp;ldquo;wtf is in a sound file&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;thinkin&#34;&gt;Thinkin&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my walk, I recorded assumptions in my Notes app - partially using voice, typing when that failed.
I hadn&amp;rsquo;t validated these, but they were the start of my train of thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humans experience sound though vibrations transmitted through the ear drum and small bones in the ear, then to the cochlea, which vibrates little hairs that send electrical signals to the brain via the auditory nerve (I think? this is why cochlear implants are so effective - they&amp;rsquo;re about as direct we can get to interacting with the brain)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To express sound, we probably need to express frequency, loudness, and &amp;hellip; &amp;ldquo;sound&amp;rdquo;? Like.. whatever makes a violin playing a C note at the same volume sound different than a piano
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(I later learned I was dancing around &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timbre&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;timbre&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to represent this data in a way that can be stored on a computer, we need to come up with a multi-dimensional representation that expresses a &amp;hellip; frame? of sound. Frame is probably the wrong way to describe it, but a snapshot of the &amp;ldquo;sound data&amp;rdquo; at a specific point in time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To &amp;ldquo;replay&amp;rdquo; the file, we need metadata that gives the player information about the sound - I assume one of the key pieces here is the rate at which we process frames? Unless that&amp;rsquo;s standard across filetypes? I doubt we&amp;rsquo;ve been able to standardize on a number but I &lt;strong&gt;believe&lt;/strong&gt; this is sample rate and is expressed in Hertz
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(bingo)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similar to pictures or binaries, the metadata is probably represented as a byte sequence in the header / first few bytes of the file. I&amp;rsquo;ve messed with hex editors before with games, I&amp;rsquo;ll just look up the .wav or .mp3 header when I get home.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.fileformat.com/audio/wav/&#34;&gt;wav file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Based on reddit threads I remember from arguments about &amp;ldquo;lossless&amp;rdquo; music, I imagine &amp;ldquo;simpler&amp;rdquo; formats (.wav) just contain less rich data about the source sound than their FLAC counterparts. Either they&amp;rsquo;re less expressive in the dimensionality of their frames and/or there are less frames per unit of time? Anyway, apparently without listening to lossless music I&amp;rsquo;m not experiencing the full glory of Modest Mouse but instead drinking what must feel like a Lemon Lime La Croix to a margarita.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;tinkering&#34;&gt;Tinkering&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.fileformat.com/audio/wav/#wav-file-header&#34;&gt;WAV File Header&lt;/a&gt;.
I downloaded a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pdx-cs-sound/wavs/blob/main/voice.wav&#34;&gt;sample wav&lt;/a&gt; file and started messing around with it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Would the Person I Want to Be Work Here?</title>
      <link>https://tdoot.com/writing/would-the-person-i-want-to-be-work-here/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 20:04:43 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tdoot.com/writing/would-the-person-i-want-to-be-work-here/</guid>
      <description>The best jobs are a forcing function for becoming the person you want to be.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Kubernetes Deployments, ReplicaSets, and HPAs coordinate</title>
      <link>https://tdoot.com/writing/understanding-k8s-deployments-replicasets-hpas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 12:01:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tdoot.com/writing/understanding-k8s-deployments-replicasets-hpas/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;#39;s walk through a real-world scenario where a Kubernetes Deployment rollout and HPA clashed yet everything was technically working. Here&amp;#39;s how these important control loops interact under pressure and how to debug autoscaling failures that don’t show up in staging.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamentals for solid kubernetes controllers</title>
      <link>https://tdoot.com/writing/building-solid-kubernetes-controllers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 17:50:05 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tdoot.com/writing/building-solid-kubernetes-controllers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the second post in my Kubernetes Controllers series. In the &lt;a href=&#34;https://tdoot.com/writing/kubernetes-controllers-explained&#34;&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt;, we explored what controllers are and how they maintain your desired state through continuous reconciliation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I explained the utility and purpose of Kubernetes Controllers. This post will explain how to build them, and how to think about designing them. We&amp;rsquo;ll go into Controller patterns, anti-patterns, and sharp edges of the model that you&amp;rsquo;re bound to run into.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kubernetes controllers explained</title>
      <link>https://tdoot.com/writing/kubernetes-controllers-explained/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 15:39:45 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tdoot.com/writing/kubernetes-controllers-explained/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the first post in my Kubernetes Controllers series. In the &lt;a href=&#34;https://tdoot.com/writing/building-solid-kubernetes-controllers&#34;&gt;second post&lt;/a&gt; I walk through how to build stable controllers from scratch.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Controllers aren&amp;rsquo;t just add-ons to Kubernetes - they&amp;rsquo;re fundamental to how the whole system works. They&amp;rsquo;re the caretakers of your cluster, overseeing and orchestrating processes to ensure your defined resources stay on track. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kubernetes/kubernetes/blob/master/pkg/controller/replicaset/replica_set.go&#34;&gt;maintaining pod replicas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kubernetes/kubernetes/blob/master/pkg/controller/deployment/deployment_controller.go&#34;&gt;managing rolling updates&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kubernetes/kubernetes/blob/master/pkg/controller/nodelifecycle/node_lifecycle_controller.go&#34;&gt;handling node lifecycles&lt;/a&gt;, controllers are there making sure things run smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My home gym primer</title>
      <link>https://tdoot.com/writing/building-a-home-gym/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 20:23:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tdoot.com/writing/building-a-home-gym/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend asked for my recommendations for home gym equipment as they wanted to start building out theirs. Little do they know I&amp;rsquo;ve spent way too many hours thinking about this. My home gym is nothing special but it keeps me healthy, out of commercial gyms, and never leaves me wishing I had more equipment. I like to think that&amp;rsquo;s due to making the right choices on how to fill it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First half of 2024 ruled</title>
      <link>https://tdoot.com/writing/first-half-of-2024-ruled/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 10:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tdoot.com/writing/first-half-of-2024-ruled/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;in roughly chronological order&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;got convinced by friends to start a magic the gathering team. took it from 6 -&amp;gt; 20 people
&lt;img alt=&#34;magic 512&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://tdoot.com/images/pictures/h1-2024/team.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;not everyone pictured&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;got engaged to my college sweetheart and the love of my life
&lt;img alt=&#34;proposal&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://tdoot.com/images/pictures/h1-2024/proposal.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;been waiting a while for this one.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;took a trip to Japan where I played in 12+ magic tournaments, got invited to dinner with locals, and found my best man
&lt;img alt=&#34;proposal&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://tdoot.com/images/pictures/h1-2024/tokyo_group.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;left to right: new tokyo magic friend, me, best man&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building nightly ghost blog backups</title>
      <link>https://tdoot.com/writing/nightly-ghost-backups/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:17:57 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tdoot.com/writing/nightly-ghost-backups/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in grad school I used to make some extra cash by coaching and writing articles about &lt;a href=&#34;https://hearthstone.blizzard.com/en-us&#34;&gt;Hearthstone&lt;/a&gt; (an online collectible card game made by Blizzard). I primarily wrote &amp;ldquo;deck techs&amp;rdquo;, guides that explained how to play the most powerful and consistent decks that were dominating the scene. I loved this job, it was a surprisingly technical creative outlet and paid for the occasional treat meals at my favorite restaurant in St. Louis, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.saltandsmokebbq.com/&#34;&gt;Salt n Smoke.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Doing kubernetes on the cheap</title>
      <link>https://tdoot.com/writing/cheap-k8s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 18:11:22 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tdoot.com/writing/cheap-k8s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most SRE-aligned engineers will tell you they have a home lab. Depending on how grey the beard is, it may be an old blade they acquired when a company moved data centers, an intricate setup of Raspberry Pi 4s set up in a custom cooling rack, or like me and many others, it may just be an old gaming computer they no longer use but cannot bring themselves to get rid of. Whatever it may be, it&amp;rsquo;s usually used for learning, tinkering, or to run some of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://reddit.com/r/selfhosted&#34;&gt;/r/selfhosted&lt;/a&gt; favorites.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;m not excited about buy now pay later</title>
      <link>https://tdoot.com/writing/bnpl-is-predatory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 19:41:40 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tdoot.com/writing/bnpl-is-predatory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a system (sigh) built on getting people to buy things they can&amp;rsquo;t reasonably afford through the veil of &amp;ldquo;it&amp;rsquo;s only X a month.&amp;rdquo;
Unnecessary consumer debt sets people up to fail by putting them on a treadmill of excess consumption they believe is under control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Dude falling off of treadmill&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/inAeEKMJ2CkdW/giphy.gif#center&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sticker shock is a good thing. If you see the price tag of something and it has your head reeling, there&amp;rsquo;s probably a good reason you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be buying it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
